喂
Hey.
不必费心了
Don't bother.
他死了
He's dead.
你也死了
You're dead too.
但这火烧得正旺
The fire isn't.
为你熬制Vicodin的doodle
冰卡送HOUSE阿好泪别HW  草草
vitaminwater  紫玉&All Hail House!
Silmar  妖月Seraphim
总监：
zlean
你是不是该起身
You might want to get up
找出口去了
and start heading for the exit signs.
我觉得
For all I know,
我已经起来了
I already am up.
更有意思的问题是
More interesting question is why would I hallucinate
为什么出现在我幻觉中的
an ex-employee who I last saw
会是你这个开枪自刎的前雇员
with a self-inflicted gunshot wound,
而不是什么
as opposed to someone more...
大波妹
busty?
劳驾给我解释一下你怎么会在这里
Care to explain why you're here?
这具尸体
The dead guy.
是谁
Who is he?
在哪里认识的
How'd you meet him?
上个月我出了场车祸
I was in a car accident last month.
我高中时还赢过游泳比赛呢
I won a swimming trophy in high school.
该你了
Your turn.
我止痛药吃完了
I-I ran out of pain medication.
但因为眶骨骨折
I got an orbital fracture.
估计要很久才会痊愈
It's just taking ages to heal.
把上衣脱了
Take off your shirt.
我的眼睛长这里
My eye's up here.
眶骨骨折说明
Orbital fracture means
你的脸撞上了挡风玻璃
your face went into the windshield,
也就是说你的胸部必定撞到了方向盘
which means your chest went into the steering wheel.
止痛药会抑制心率
Painkillers can suppress heart rate,
除非你不想活了
so unless you want me to kill you,
否则就老老实实脱衣服让我做个心脏检查
take off your shirt, let me do a heart exam.
我还想看看
I also wanted to see the ring of burns
你锁骨边的烧伤环
around your collarbone.
你怎么知道的
How'd you know?
你跟护士说对可待因类药物过敏
The codeine allergy you told the nurse about.
潜台词就是  给我下点猛药吧
That's shorthand for "Give me the strong stuff,"
挺称你散发着"爷也牛逼过"愤懑的装束
which matches your seen-better-days-because-my-life-fell-apart suit.
手指两处旧烫伤伤口
The two old burns on your fingers
估计是你边抽烟边打盹的误伤
mean you tend to nod off with a cigarette in your hand.
所以叼嘴里掉下来也不足为奇
No reason you shouldn't do that with one in your mouth.
上帝保佑你能多遇见些蠢医生
May all your doctors be stupid.
等等
Hold on a second.
脐周有挫伤
That bruising around your belly button.
看来你要的猛药
Well, you might get some fun drugs
有着落了
out of this after all.
出现卡伦氏征
Cullen's sign.
但B超显示有血气腹征象
But the ultrasound showed air as well as blood.
我知道你在想什么
Now, I know what you're thinking.
出血性胰腺炎
Hemorrhagic pancreatitis.
我来说说我怎么想
But I also know what I'm thinking.
这无法解释气腹问题
Doesn't explain the pneuomoperitoneum.
你接了个新病例
You took a new case?
你自己做了化验
You ran tests yourself?
看到需要帮助的人
I saw the chance to help someone in need,
我本能地
and I instinctively--
也不是啦  这是别人的本能
oh, no, wait, that was someone else's instinct.
威尔森快不行了
Wilson is dying.
你的假释官说不定
Your parole officer is probably
已经在来这里逮你的路上了
on his way here right now.
你怎么还笑得出来
How are you possibly in a good mood?
你没看过《死亡诗社》[电影]吗
Did you never see Dead Poets Society?
及时行乐
Carpe diem.
腹部积气说明
Air in his abdomen could mean
那个那个那个那个
Blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
但这个这个这个这个
But blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
什么  什么什么
Blah. Blah, blah.
没人关心怎么诊断
Nobody cares about the medicine.
显然是消化道溃疡性穿孔
It was perforated ulcer.
剖开肚子  补好窟窿
Laparotomy to find the hole in his tummy and close it up.
你没有回答你团队的问题
You didn't answer the team's question.
感觉真诡异  因为通常
Which is weird, because normally,
我跟我自己部下说话
when I talk to my own employees,
都要先宣个誓  再接个测谎仪
I'm under oath and hooked up to a lie detector.
你面临的可是六个月的牢狱之灾
You were looking at six months of prison
将无法陪威尔森度过余生最后的五个月生命
instead of five months of Wilson.
-有什么可乐的  -我早计上心头了
- Why happy? - Obviously I had a plan.
全世界都知道你主意多
Obviously, obviously you had a plan.
我比较感兴趣的是
The more interesting question
你为什么不告诉你的团队
is why you didn't tell the team.
我猜是因为在潜意识里你一开始就觉得
I think it's because part of you knew from the start
这计划没戏
that the plan wouldn't work.
我想跟你谈谈
I need a meeting.
忙着呢  打到我办公室约
I'm busy. Call my office.
倒也是
Yes...
歪了的桌子怎么可能自己站直
Because wobbly tables don't just unwobble themselves.
我有事找你
I need a meeting.
多谢你抽空招待我
Thanks for fitting me in.
我的团队接下了八个重症病例
My team has eight urgent, life-or-death cases.
他们还等着我回去裁决
That they've been waiting for me
是受理还是放弃呢
to accept or reject.
你就给我吹吧
When is that not true?
好吧  实话说  目前就一个
Well, right now, for one.
你就告诉假释委员会说我准备接手八例
But tell my parole board that I'm taking all eight...
没人能解的案子
that no one else can crack them,
接下来的五个月你需要我留在这里
that you need me here for the next five months
否则那八条人命就没了
or eight people will die.
你在请求我做伪证
You're asking me to perjure myself.
这只是一个小小的善意的谎言[白色谎言]
It's a tiny, white lie.
恕我无心讽刺
No offense.
特别是自从  就我所闻
Especially since, from what I hear,
万物黑则硕  之后
nothing black is tiny.
不过我猜你的小弟弟例外
Except your penis, I guess.
你真觉得我主观上想让天花板塌陷的吗
You really think I wanted to cave in that ceiling?
那只是个出现意外的恶作剧
It was a prank that went wrong.
废我点工资吧  告我吧
Dock my pay, sue me--
违反重罪会给你的判决上
Felony vandalism should have added
再添一两年
another year or two to your sentence.
假释委员会同意只判六个月已经是奇迹了
It's a miracle the parole board agreed to six months.
不管如何  我最后都会进监狱
I will go to jail, eventually.
我会付出代价接受惩罚
I will pay the price.
我只是不想威尔森受罪
I just rather that Wilson didn't.
拜托  交个朋友
Come on, be a friend.
好吧
Okay.
不过不管你有什么案例  你得全数拿下
But whatever cases you have, you have to take them all.
"交个朋友"
"Be a friend"?
我竖着几根手指
How many fingers am I holding up?
你当然知道是三根了
Of course you know it's three,
因为你知我所知
because you know everything I know.
我那重击混乱着的大脑可以记住所有事
Everything my smack-addled brain can remember,
包括我确切地说了  交个朋友  这句话
including that I actually said, "Be a friend."
我的重点不是你说了这话
My point wasn't that you said it.
重点是  我再说一次  为什么
My point was, once again, why?
我认为  是因为你内心知道
I think it's because part of you knew
你需要朋友
you were gonna need a friend.
你内心知道那计划
Part of you knew the plan,
即便是顺利进行  也全然无效
even when it was working, wouldn't work.
而现在我所好奇的是
And right now, I'm curious about
为什么你坐在地板上
why you're sitting on the ground
而没有向门那边走
instead of heading for the door.
我们应该都弄懂了为什么你会看到我
Guess we figured out why you're seeing me,
你自行了断的朋友
your suicidal friend.
他会每天给你打两次电话
He'll call you twice a day.
然后他的夫人也会每天给你打两次电话
Then his wife will call you twice a day
确保她明白丈夫向她转述的你的话
to make sure she understands what he told her you told him,
可实际上她不会明白  因为他丈夫不会去转述
which she won't because he didn't.
也许你想把这案子交给康纳斯
Maybe you want to give this one to Connors.
豪斯在哪里
Where's house?
不知道  不关心
Don't know, don't care.
我正在工作
Working.
不好意思
Excuse me.
两天了  音信全无
No one has seen or heard from him
没人见过他
since two nights ago.
我敢保证他现在正爽着呢
I'm sure he's enjoying himself.
上一次他进监狱的时候
Last time he went to prison,
他刷爆了信用卡
he maxed out his credit cards.
上一次他进监狱的时候
Last time he went to prison,
他认为有你等他
he thought he had you waiting for him.
你觉得他会做出什么傻事吗
You think he could've done something stupid?
我认为他做傻事就已经是谢天谢地了
I think stupid is our best-case scenario.
你为什么要自杀呢
Why do you want to kill yourself?
理由如下
Well, here's a reason.
我甚至不能用毒品的快感来摆脱一个混蛋
I can't even get stoned without some annoying jerk
对我指手划脚  认定我需深度分析
deciding I need to be deeply analyzed.
这难道不就是一个简单到愚蠢的数学题吗
Isn't this just an incredibly simple calculation?
我要进监狱了
I'm going to jail,
要失业  要失去最好的朋友
losing my job, losing my best friend.
还要再说下去吗
Do I need more?
你以为那就是作为豪斯的全部吗
You think that's the sum total of who you are?
一个医生  威尔森的好友吗
A doctor? A friend to Wilson?
我还是一个超棒的男中音
I'm also a tremendous baritone.
现在一边去
Now go away.
即便是在你的潜意识中  你也是个逃避的人
Even with your subconscious, you're evasive.
死亡并不有趣
Death's not interesting.
你是为趣味而生的
You exist for what's interesting.
谜题啊  点子啊  分析啊
Puzzles, ideas, analysis.
死亡是炫目谜题的对立面
Death is the opposite of a cool puzzle.
是无尽的空虚
It's eternal nothingness.
但是你发现生命也了无生趣了
But you don't find life interesting anymore.
别傻了
Stop being an idiot.
请问能让卡特那回来吗
Can I have Kutner back, please?
我还要看多久的苦情戏啊
How much pathetic wallowing do I have to sit through?
地狱怎么样
How are things in hell?
湿度是个大问题吧
Is the humidity the big issue?
这家伙的病后来怎么样了
What happened next with the guy's medical case?
-为什么问这个  -没错
- Why? - Exactly.
为什么我  也就是你
Why am I, meaning you,
仍在痴迷于这一病例
still obsessing about this case?
显然跟我们为什么仍安坐在
Obviously we think it's relevant to
失火大楼的地板上有关
why we're still sitting on the floor of a burning building.
他经历过一次急救
There was a code.
他肺部有血块
Gotta be a clot in his lungs.
得马上送他去手术室
We need to get him to an O.R.
没时间了  他的血氧饱和度在下降
No time. His O-2 stats are falling.
得在这里吸出来  床边血栓清除术
We have to suck it out here. Bedside embolectomy.
漂浮导管通过心脏
Float a catheter through his heart
他的血氧状态会更糟
and his oxygenation will get even worse.
我们还没完成他就会送命的
He'll die before we can finish the procedure.
豪斯  你快做决定
House, we need a call here.
你干什么
What are you doing?
你给他用什么了
What did you give him?
五  四
Five, four...
三  二
Three, two...
纳络酮
Naloxone.
看到他那个自称叫"焦白粉"的表兄来拜访他
We should've got suspicious when his visiting cousin
我们就该心中有数了
signed in as "Mr. Tar H. Horse."
海络因导致呼吸窘迫
Heroin caused the respiratory distress.
纳络酮封闭了吗啡受体
The naloxone turned off the receptors,
结果就这样了
caused your distress.
我不会停止吸毒
I'm not gonna stop doing drugs!
现实悲剧透了
It's reality that sucks!
你想说我这是在欺骗
You're saying I'm lying...
自己的潜意识吗
to my subconscious?
人之常情
People do it all the time.
无论你喜不喜欢  你也是人
And like it or not, you are a person.
-那些话都是他说的  -但不是此情
- He said every one of those things. - But not then
不是此景
and not like that.
纳络酮让他失去了理智
This guy was going nuts from the naloxone.
只要你想  他就无法保持理性
He couldn't be rational if you wanted him to be,
你还真就想
which you did.
为什么
Why?
-故事虽略有加工  -情境才是关键
- I compressed the story a little-- - Context matters.
你从不为与诊断无关的事情跟病人聊天
You never talk to patients for non-diagnostic reasons,
但这个人
but this guy...
好点了吗
Feeling better?
我不会停止吸毒
I'm not gonna stop doing drugs.
你以前是股票经纪人
You were a stockbroker.
你父亲是股票经纪人
Son of a stockbroker.
-你有妻子  有孩子  -我很痛苦
- Married, children. - I was miserable.
你说你很痛苦
Well, you say you were miserable
是为了给自己的一败涂地找借口
because you need to rationalize screwing it up.
我没有找借口
Except I didn't.
我是说  我是一败涂地
I mean, I-I did.
但我不痛苦了  不再痛苦了
But I'm not miserable. Not anymore.
我滑雪受过伤
I had a ski injury
而止痛药不够强效
and painkillers weren't enough,
一位朋友给了我点海洛因
and a friend of mine gave me some heroin.
毒品一进入我的血管
The second it entered my veins,
就好像上帝抚慰了我的身体
it was like God had taken over my body.
似乎这世界上所有的痛苦
It was like there was no more pain
所有的不幸  都离我远去  离所有人远去
or unhappiness in my life or anybody else's.
但之后你失去了一切
But then you lost everything.
那所谓的"一切"并不够
Everything wasn't enough.
因为现实悲剧透了
Because it's reality that sucks.
你在辩说他是行为模范吗
Are you arguing that he's a good role model?
-他快乐了  -他死了
- He's happy. - He's dead.
你只听自己想听的
You heard what you wanted to hear.
最有趣的地方
The more interesting question--
永远都是  你为什么想听那些
always--is why you wanted to hear it.
你在偷吸他的氧气
You're stealing this guy's oxygen?
氧气到处都有
There's oxygen everywhere.
你把你的病例全移交了
You passed on all your cases,
扔给了其他的医生
reassigned them to other doctors.
那些病例太无趣了
They weren't interesting.
那些病例才是我要推迟对你判决的原因
They were my reason for getting your sentence delayed!
是啊  那我看
Yeah, well, I guess you'll have to tell
你得跟假释裁决委员会说点别的了
the parole board something else.
比如天花板倒塌那天
Maybe that I was in the O.R.
我一整天都在手术室
the entire day the ceiling collapsed,
所以不可能是我造成的水管问题
so I couldn't have caused the plumbing problem.
-你设计我  -也不算啦
- You set me up. - Not really.
你原本就要出庭作"伪证"
You were going to basically perjure yourself
好让我推迟入狱
so that I could delay jail time.
你干脆出庭作伪证
Doesn't it make more sense to actually perjure yourself
好让我不必入狱岂非更好
so that I can actually avoid jail time?
你为什么要这么做
Why are you doing this?
为什么要冒险自我毁灭
Why are you risking destroying yourself?
没什么冒险的  我了解你
There's no risk. I know you.
你会如实处事
You'll do the honest thing.
你会撒谎
You'll lie.
我不会
No.
他快乐了
He's happy.
他死了
He's dead.
你并没有担心
You weren't worried.
我当然担心了  我的计划失败了
Of course I was worried. My plan fell through.
计划不是重点
The plan didn't matter.
你的第二个计划也不重要
Your plan to replace that plan didn't matter.
威尔森不重要  监狱不重要
Wilson didn't matter. Jail didn't matter.
唯一要紧的事
The only thing that mattered,
自始至终唯一要紧的事
the only thing that ever mattered,
就是谜题
was the puzzle.
我发现他的鱼际有轻微的抽搐
I noticed a slight twitch in his thenar eminence,
这说明...
which meant...
你就要死了
you're dying.
就因为我拇指抖了一下
Because my thumb's a little shaky?
加上拇指上的肌肉萎缩
Plus the thinning in the muscle,
加上你在洋基体育场发表的演讲
plus that speech you gave at yankee stadium
说什么你是这世上
saying you were the luckiest man
最幸运的男人
on the face of the earth.
全部加起来就是肌萎缩侧索硬化症
Add them up, it means ALS.
鲁盖瑞氏症吗
Lou Gehrig's disease?
被自己的身体困住  不能行动不能说话
You're trapped in your body, you can't move or speak
就这样死去
while you just die.
如果能对你有些安慰
If it makes you feel any better,
以目前的速度  不会拖太久
at this rate, it'll be fast.
你的肌力不对称
You're not symmetrical.
等等
Wait.
现在你站在门前了
Now you're standing at the door.
这之间发生了什么事
What happened in the meantime?
真难想象  奇迹般的事情发生了
And lo, there was a miraculous wonder--
我从房间一头走到了另一头
I walked across the room.
不  你跳过了一大段的对话
No, you just skipped over a chunk of conversation.
他发了誓会在所剩时间内
He swore that he would live a better
让自己做一个更好更无私的人
and more selfless life in his remaining time,
废话连篇
blah, blah, blah.
听两句我就受够了
After two blahs, I'd heard enough.
走向了门口
I moved to the door.
不  你是在躲避
No, you're avoiding it.
你有闻到烟味吗
Do you smell smoke?
好吧  这次就算了
Fair enough.
你的肌力不对称
You're not symmetrical.
右侧静脉曲张
The veins on your right side are distended.
那是什么意思
What does that mean?
锁骨上窝隆起
There's a bulge in your superclavicular notch.
里面有东西
There's something in there.
什么东西
What?
我没你想的那么神奇
Well, I'm not that good a doctor.
好消息
Good news.
你的病例非常有趣
Your case is fascinating.
告诉你个好消息
And good news for you:
你会活下来的
you're gonna live.
你吸入了一根小小的树枝
You've inhaled a small branch,
大概是你晕倒在公园里的长椅上
probably while you were realizing that it's all
突然发觉活着还挺有意义的时候
worth it while you were passed out on a park bench.
其他人会把它咳出来
Anyone else would have coughed it up,
但是因为你吸毒过多
but 'cause you're a junkie,
你的咳嗽反射被抑制了
your cough reflex is suppressed.
它就这样长大了
And it grew?
别傻了  如果你还吸入了太阳
Not unless you also inhaled a chunk of the sun
和一个滴灌系统倒是有可能
and a drip-irrigation system, you idiot.
只是引发了自身免疫反应  而这
It set off an auto-immune reaction, which--
我忍不住得说
I can't help saying this--
这就是你问题的"根"本
Was the root of all your problems.
你笑了
You're smiling.
我刚才是笑了  现在没有了
I was, and now I'm not,
因为几天前一瞬间的乐趣
because a moment's fun a few days ago
抵不过友人将死的悲痛
does not trump a friend dying.
别傻了  乐趣当首  你个白痴
Yeah, it does, you idiot.
他死了之后  你会哭一阵
'Cause after he's dead, you cry for a while,
然后继续做你爱做的事情
and then you go back to doing what you love.
我治疗过的每一位病患
Every patient that I've had,
70年后的今天  他们和威尔森一样都会死
70 years from now, they'll all be as dead as Wilson.
谁都会死  治疗他们毫无意义
Everybody dies. It's meaningless.
但当你解开一个谜题  世界就有了意义
When you solve a puzzle, the world makes sense,
一切自如
everything feels right.
而且你的谜题会源源不断
And you'll always have another one,
因为时时刻刻都有人会得病
because people always get sick.
虽然这想法肤浅  毫无价值
It's shallow and it's insignificant,
但如果你对人命都毫不在乎
but if you don't give a damn if idiots live,
又怎么会介意肤浅呢
why would you possibly give a damn about shallowness?
谜题让你开心
It makes you happy.
你还需要什么呢
And why would you need more than that?
回家吧
Go home.
福曼
Foreman!
豪斯是绝不会让食物就这样馊掉的
House would never leave food out here rotting for days.
他的行李箱还在衣橱里
His suitcases are in his closet.
要是我们当时换种方式处理此事
If we had handled this differently--
我们没有做错
We did the right thing.
喂
Hello?
我会转告他的会计
I'll let his accountant know.
豪斯两晚前没去找一个妓女
House no-showed on a hooker two nights ago.
呼出电话
Outgoing calls.
妓女
Hooker...
我...我没接
Me... I didn't pick up.
中餐馆
Chinese place...
慢着  这是谁
Wait, wait, wait. Who's that?
他打了四通电话
He called four times.
不知道
I don't know.
真是场灾难
It's a total disaster.
我工作时间那么长
Do you have any idea how hard it is
就连做个有线电视的预约
to schedule a cable appointment
都难上青天
with the hours that I work?
豪斯失踪两天了
House has been missing for two days.
我们知道他跟你通过话
We know he talked to you.
你能告诉我们他的精神状态
Anything you can tell us about his mental state,
或去向吗  任何事都行
or where he was headed-- anything at all--
那就违反了保密协议  也是违法的
Would be a breach of confidentiality and a violation of the law.
除非他可能伤害自己或他人
Not if he's a danger to himself or someone else.
这会从我们的五十分钟里扣吗
Is this coming out of our 50 minutes?
这是你的二逼组吗
Is this your douche bag group?
失陪一下
Excuse me.
你们为什么认为他会伤害自己
What makes you think he's a danger to himself?
他没回家
He hasn't been home,
却没随身带走任何东西  连手机都没带
but he didn't take anything with him, not even his cell.
你沉默不语
You're not saying anything,
说明他没有明确提到过自杀
which means he didn't specifically mention suicide,
但你出来跟我们说话
but you came out here to talk to us,
那他肯定是说了什么让你担心的话
so he must have said something that worries you.
还有其它方式能使人失去意识
There are other ways of reaching oblivion.
-维科丁吗  -他一直嗑维科丁
- Vicodin? - He always has his vicodin.
他没必要打电话给心理...
There's no reason to call a shr--
他最后一个病人是瘾君子
His last patient was a heroin addict.
那我们没事了吧
So I guess we're all done here.
他的地址肯定在档案里
The guy's address has gotta be in the file.
那上帝呢
What about god?
你刚才要走的  却又留下了
You were leaving, and then you stopped.
为什么
Why?
你认为我不走  是因为我信上帝
Your theory is I'm not leaving, because I believe in god?
怎么  他喊我回家吃饭了
What, he's calling me home?
或许从地板上掉下来是个启示呢
Maybe falling through that floor was a sign.
或许这世界恨你  什么的
Maybe that the universe hates you--something.
你真的不信吗
You really don't believe?
真的吗  在你内心
Really? Not in some deep crack
某个阴暗角落的裂口深处  也完全不信吗
of some remote recess of some dark corner of your mind?
没有
No.
但我内心
Except that some deep crack
某个阴暗角落的裂口深处
of some remote recess of some dark corner
-有个声音在对我说  -这就足够了
- is here telling me- - That's enough.
在一栋燃烧的大楼里
In a burning building,
死亡步步逼近  这就足够了
facing imminent death, that's more than enough.
帕斯卡的赌注认为人应信上帝
但是上帝是否真的存在永不得而知
帕斯卡的赌注就是小聪明
Pascal's wager is facile.
说他耍小聪明也是一种小聪明
Saying it's facile is facile.
为什么就不对
Why is it wrong?
别那么理智  绝望一点
And don't be logical. Be desperate.
你总得有个支撑
You gotta have something to hold on to.
你不能把人生建构在你不相信的东西上
You can't live your life based on something you don't believe.
那你就能为你不信的东西结束生命了吗
But you can end your life based on something you don't believe?
那么爱呢
What about love?
我曾跟你生活多年
I lived with you for years.
我知道你相信爱
I know you believe in love.
福曼不肯帮我
Foreman wouldn't help me,
所以我需要你替我顶罪
which means I need you to take the fall.
你还记得我就要死了吧
You do remember I'm dying, right?
所以说你能免去牢狱之灾
Which is why you will never spend a day in jail.
没前科又受癌症折磨
Fresh-faced, cancer-ridden.
同时做到两者不容易  你还是做到了
It's tough to do both, but you pull it off.
那些球票上都是你的指纹
Your fingerprints are all over those hockey tickets.
但我没承认冲下过任何东西
I never admitted to flushing anything.
有我指纹能说得通
My prints make sense
比如我把票给了你
if I gave those tickets to you
激励你活下去
as an incentive to stay alive.
而你不尊重我寻死的意愿令我勃然大怒
And I was so angry that you didn't respect my dying wishes,
以至于把上千元的季票
I took thousands of dollars of season tickets
冲下下水道吗
and flushed them down toilets?
你只需要制造合理疑点
All you have to do is create reasonable doubt.
好啊  如果我做过头了呢
Great, what if I do more than that?
如果我进了班房呢
What if I end up in jail?
或是浪费最后的时光在各种听证会上了呢
Or spending my final months in endless hearings?
那是你甘愿冒的险
That is a risk you are willing to take.
我是有声誉的
I have a reputation.
我还能留下...
I have a legacy that could--
威尔森
Wilson...
我不想失去有你在的最后时光
I don't want to lose this time with you.
好吧
Okay.
谢谢
Thanks.
就知道我能指望你
I knew I could count on you.
等等  等等
Wait! Wait.
想要回你的薯条吗
You want the fries back?
我不会替你顶罪的
I'm not gonna take the fall.
别这么对我  威尔森
Don't do this to me, Wilson.
这是我们唯一的选择
This is our only option.
没错  因为你跟福曼玩过火了
Exactly, because you overplayed your hand with Foreman,
因为你知道还有我能给你擦屁股
because you knew you had me as a backstop.
我都要死了
Even with me dying,
你也想当然地认为我会助你脱离窘境
you just assumed I'd be here to bail you out.
可你的确来了
Since you're here,
也打算帮我脱离窘境
and you are bailing me out,
看来我想得没错啊
seems like a pretty safe assumption.
很快我就不在了
I won't be here soon.
我要是帮了你  就是在教你
If I do this, I'm teaching you
你做错事还总能得到甜头
that your bad behavior will always be rewarded.
你需要学会
You need to learn--
你不在了要如何处事吗
How to act when you're gone?
如果这就是我要长的教训
'cause if that's the lesson,
我们马上就有个不错的机会
we got a really great opportunity coming up.
出了事你只会找别人帮忙
You'll just try to find someone else,
但那没用  也不该有用
and it won't work, and it shouldn't work!
这就是你要传授给我的真知灼见吗
So that's the great wisdom you're imparting?
我永远都会孤身一人
That I'll always be alone?
这世上你只能指望一个人
There's only one person you can count on.
我还以为有两个
I thought there were two.
我必须这么做...
I need to do this...
为了你好
for you.
威尔森是对的
Wilson's right.
他一直是对的
He's always right.
他总是充当你的善心[好看的一面]
He's always been your good side.
怪不得我照相总那么难看
I always wondered why I photographed so poorly.
因为他总是做大好人
And because he's always played that role,
所以你从来不用长良心
you've never had to develop a conscience of your own.
人是不会变的
People don't change.
良心也不会自己长出来
Consciences don't spontaneously develop.
你错了  格雷戈
You're wrong, Greg.
所以说...
Which is...
没有他  对你反而更好
why you'll be better off without him.
你一直依赖他
You've been looking to him
来寻找你自身的东西
to find what you have gotta find within yourself.
这是你能找到的
Something you can find.
抱抱你的孩子
Hold your child.
这正是我该去死的理由
This is a reason to die.
我的人生本可如此
This is what my life could've been,
现在却不可能了
not what it can be.
既然曾经可能
If it could've been,
现在也为时不晚
you're capable of it now.
你结婚了  卡迪走了
You're married. Cuddy's gone.
世上并不只有我们两个人会爱你
We aren't the only two people who could love you.
干嘛就这么容易满足
Why settle so easily?
这些只是不切实际的幻想...
These are just idiotic fantasies...
格雷戈  不要
Greg, don't.
跟我身体里的全部理智做斗争
...at odds with every logical bone in my body.
起来
Get up.
你犯不着死在这里
You do not have to die in here!
这就是地狱吗
Is this hell?
永远都有人跑来劝我活下去
An eternity of people trying to convince me to live?
谁说我是来劝你活下去的
Who says I'm here to convince you to live?
真没想到你竟然会恨我
You're the last one I thought would hate me.
我不恨你
I don't hate you.
我爱你
I love you.
但你认为我应该去死
And yet you think I deserve to die.
但不是作为惩罚
But not as a punishment.
而是作为奖励
As a reward.
我认为...你经受得够多了
I think... you've suffered enough.
也付出得够多了
You've given enough.
我认为你应该获得一个...
I think you deserve a chance to just...
放弃的机会
give up.
就像威尔森那样
Like Wilson did?
Like Wilson did.
你接受了他的选择
You accepted his choice,
结束痛苦好过忍受痛苦
that ending the pain was better than the pain.
为什么你不能如此厚待自己呢
Why can't you give yourself that gift?
这就是豪斯的病人给的地址吗
This is the address House's patient gave?
看来人人都撒谎
Everybody lies.
闻到烟味了吗
You smell smoke?
放手吧
Just let go.
就这样睡去
Just go to sleep.
我本有机会避免这一切的
I had a chance to avoid this.
你有过很多机会  但你把它们都毁了
You had many chances, and you blew them all up.
不  这次不一样
No, this was different.
每次都不一样
They're all different,
但理由都是一样的
but the reasons are all the same.
你傲慢  有自毁倾向
You're arrogant. You're self-destructive.
你只关心你自己
You only care about yourself.
和病人一起的时候
That moment with the patient...
我跳过的那段对话
The chunk of the conversation I skipped over...
我告诉他他就要死了
I told him he was dying.
如果能对你有些安慰
If it makes you feel any better,
以目前的速度  不会拖太久
at this rate, it'll be fast.
我替你顶罪吧
Let me take the fall.
你的那个恶作剧
For you, for that prank.
你不欠我什么
You don't owe me anything.
-你努力救过我  -但我失败了
- You tried to save me. - I failed.
动机不重要  重要的是行动
Motives don't matter. Only actions.
努力也是一种行动
Trying is an action.
你为什么还要劝我别帮你
Why are you trying to talk me out of this?
你只管伪造记录
You just fake the records.
说我是上周来看的门诊
You say I came into the clinic last week.
我就告诉警察  你态度恶劣
I'll tell the cops you treated me like crap,
所以我偷了你的票冲进下水道
so I stole your tickets and flushed 'em.
谢谢
Thank you.
你是因为要死了才帮的我
And you're doing this because you're dying?
我这样做是因为我没什么可失去的了
I'm doing this because I have nothing left to lose.
你活得好好的时候从不帮助任何人
So when you were living, you did nothing for anyone
也毫不在意  现在你要死了
and you didn't care. Now that you're dying,
倒乐意对陌生人伸出援手
you're willing to help a virtual stranger.
垂死之际  你变得比以往任何时候都善良
Which means you're a better person dying than you ever were living,
我没能救你反倒令世界更美好
and the world is a better place because I didn't save you.
令我不禁怀疑自己为什么要告诉你
Which makes me wonder why I'm about to tell you...
你的肌力不对称
You're not symmetrical.
你想说明什么
What's your point?
你关心他胜过你自己吗
That you cared about him more than you cared about yourself?
你是关心谜题胜过关心自己
You cared about the puzzle more than you cared about yourself.
我要是没说
If I kept it to myself,
那就仅仅是个谜题
then it would just be a puzzle,
可我既然开了口  就是因为不止如此
but I opened my mouth because I thought it was more.
你知道根本没有差别
You know it's the same,
不然你就不会火烧到脚下
or you wouldn't be bickering with me
还在和我争吵
while the flames lick at your feet.
你害怕这个决定
You're afraid of this decision,
不停与我争辩不过是想拖到无路可走
and you are trying to argue until fate takes it out of your hands.
你选了一种懦弱的方式
You're taking the cowardly way out.
更糟糕的是
And worse...
你懦弱到甚至不敢承认
You're too cowardly to even admit
你的选择有多懦弱
you're taking the cowardly way out.
你说对了
You're right.
但我还能改变
But I can change.
他本可以出来的
He could've gotten out.
也不是没可能幸存  即便是在...
People are found sometimes, even in...
倒塌的...
collapsed...
好像找到了一具尸体
I think they're pulling a body out.
法医确认是他
Coroner confirms it's him.
走投无路时是他聘用了我
House hired me when no one else would.
他害我被解雇
He got me fired.
他给了我被解雇的勇气
He gave me the guts to get fired.
他给了我辞职的勇气
He gave me the courage to quit.
格利高里...
Gregory was...
他是个好儿子
He was a good son.
他是个讨人厌的男友
He was a trying boyfriend,
可是我
but I...
从没停止过爱他
never stopped loving him.
他是我真正意义上的丈夫
He was my husband for real.
我无法自拔地爱上了他
I couldn't help but love him.
他是我上司
He was my boss.
后来又成了我的下属
And my employee.
无论何时
And both times...
我都能从他身上学到东西
I learned from him.
他让我成为了更好的父亲
He made me a better parent,
无论有意无意
whether he meant to or not.
他愿意帮我结束生命
He was willing to kill me.
我永远都感激他
And I'll always be grateful.
他通常不是很容易相处
He wasn't always easy to deal with.
但在内心深处
But somewhere in there...
他懂得如何去爱
he knew how to love.
他是我的朋友
He was my friend.
我们必须...
The thing you have to...
记住的是...
remember...
我们不能忘记
The thing you can't forget
格利高里·豪斯
is that Gregory House
救死扶伤
saved lives.
他是一名医者
He was a healer.
到头来
And... and in the end...
豪斯就是个混蛋
House was an ass.
他嘲笑所有人
He mocked anyone...
病人  同事  为数不多的朋友
patients, co-workers, his dwindling friends...
所有达不到他心里疯狂的正直标准的人
anyone who didn't measure up to his insane ideals of integrity.
他声称自己勇于探索真相
He claimed to be on some heroic quest for truth,
真相就是  他是个尖酸刻薄的混蛋
but the truth is, he was a bitter jerk
以折磨他人为乐
who liked making people miserable.
他完全不顾及别人的感受
And he proved that by dying selfishly,
注射麻醉剂  自私地死去  就证明了这一点
numbed by narcotics, without a thought of anyone.
他背叛了所有在乎他的人
A betrayal of everyone who cared about him.
手机响了
Phone.
多少次他需要我时  我都在
A million times he needed me,
而当我需要他的时候  就这一次...
and the one time that I needed him--
拜托  这可是葬礼
Oh, come on. This is a funeral.
接了吧
Just get it.
真尴尬
This is embarrassing.
我发誓已经关机了
Could've sworn I turned this off.
这不是我的手机
This isn't my phone.
你怎么...
How...
我从那幢楼的后面出去了
I got out of the back of the building.
那尸体...
The body--
牙科记录被我偷梁换柱了
Just switched the dental records.
你毁了你的整个人生
You're destroying your entire life.
这下你无路可退了
You can't go back from this.
你会坐好几年牢的
You'll go to jail for years.
再也不能当医生了
You can never be a doctor again.
我已经死了  威尔森
I'm dead, Wilson.
最后五个月生命  你想怎么度过
How do you want to spend your last five months?
等癌症越来越严重的时候...
When the cancer starts getting really bad...
癌症多无聊啊
Cancer's boring.
THE END
全剧终